As the highest military commander of the Netherlands.
[AI] 作为荷兰最高军事指挥官。
with troops stationed around the world.
[AI] 驻扎在世界各地的军队。
I'm really honored to be here today.
[AI] 今天能来到这里我真的很荣幸。
When I look around this TEDxAmsterdam venue.
[AI] 当我环顾TEDxAmsterdam会场时。
I see a very special audience.
[AI] 我看到一个非常特别的观众。
You are the reason why I said yes
[AI] 你就是我答应的原因
to the invitation to come here today.
[AI] 感谢你今天来这里的邀请。
When I look around. I see people who want to make a contribution.
[AI] 当我环顾四周。我看到有人想做出贡献。
I see people who want to make a better world.
[AI] 我看到有人想创造一个更美好的世界。
by doing groundbreaking scientific work.
[AI] 通过做开创性的科学工作。
by creating impressive works of art.
[AI] 通过创作令人印象深刻的艺术作品。
by writing critical articles or inspiring books.
[AI] 通过写评论文章或鼓舞人心的书。
by starting up sustainable businesses.
[AI] 通过创办可持续发展的企业。
And you all have chosen your own instruments
[AI] 你们都选择了自己的乐器
to fulfill this mission of creating a better world.
[AI] 完成创造更美好世界的使命。
Some chose the microscope as their instrument.
[AI] 有些人选择显微镜作为他们的仪器。
Others chose dancing or painting.
[AI] 其他人选择跳舞或绘画。
or making music like we just heard.
[AI] 或者像我们刚刚听到的那样做音乐。
Some chose the pen.
[AI] 有些人选择了钢笔。
Others work through the instrument of money.
[AI] 其他人通过货币工具工作。
Ladies and gentlemen. I made a different choice.
[AI] 女士们，先生们。我做了一个不同的选择。
Thanks.
[AI] 谢谢
Ladies and gentlemen ...
[AI] 女士们，先生们。。。
(Laughter)
[AI] （众笑）
(Applause)
[AI] （掌声）
I share your goals.
[AI] 我同意你的目标。
I share the goals of the speakers you heard before.
[AI] 我与你以前听到的发言者的目标相同。
I did not choose to take up the pen.
[AI] 我没有选择拿起那支笔。
the brush. the camera.
[AI] 刷子。照相机。
I chose this instrument.
[AI] 我选择了这种乐器。
I chose the gun.
[AI] 我选择了枪。
For you. and you heard already.
[AI] 为你。你已经听说了。
being so close to this gun may make you feel uneasy.
[AI] 离这把枪这么近可能会让你感到不安。
It may even feel scary.
[AI] 这甚至可能让人感到害怕。
A real gun at a few feet's distance.
[AI] 几英尺远的真枪。
Let us stop for a moment and feel this uneasiness.
[AI] 让我们停下来，感受一下这种不安。
You could even hear it.
[AI] 你甚至可以听到。
Let us cherish the fact
[AI] 让我们珍惜这个事实
that probably most of you have never been close to a gun.
[AI] 也许你们中的大多数人从未接近过枪。
It means the Netherlands is a peaceful country.
[AI] 这意味着荷兰是一个和平的国家。
The Netherlands is not at war.
[AI] 荷兰没有处于战争状态。
It means soldiers are not needed to patrol our streets.
[AI] 这意味着不需要士兵来巡逻我们的街道。
Guns are not a part of our lives.
[AI] 枪不是我们生活的一部分。
In many countries. it is a different story.
[AI] 在许多国家。这是一个不同的故事。
In many countries. people are confronted with guns.
[AI] 在许多国家。人们面临着枪支。
They are oppressed.
[AI] 他们受到压迫。
They are intimidated --
[AI] 他们被吓坏了--
by warlords.
[AI] 由军阀控制。
by terrorists.
[AI] 恐怖分子。
by criminals.
[AI] 犯罪分子。
Weapons can do a lot of harm.
[AI] 武器会造成很大的伤害。
They are the cause of much distress.
[AI] 他们是造成许多痛苦的原因。
Why then am I standing before you with this weapon?
[AI] 那我为什么拿着这个武器站在你面前？
Why did I choose the gun as my instrument?
[AI] 我为什么选择枪作为我的工具？
Today I want to tell you why.
[AI] 今天我想告诉你为什么。
Today I want to tell you
[AI] 今天我想告诉你
why I chose the gun to create a better world.
[AI] 为什么我选择枪来创造一个更美好的世界。
And I want to tell you how this gun can help.
[AI] 我想告诉你这把枪有什么用。
My story starts in the city of Nijmegen
[AI] 我的故事从奈梅根市开始
in the east of the Netherlands.
[AI] 在荷兰东部。
the city where I was born.
[AI] 我出生的城市。
My father was a hardworking baker.
[AI] 我父亲是一位勤奋的面包师。
but when he had finished work in the bakery.
[AI] 但当他在面包店完成工作时。
he often told me and my brother stories.
[AI] 他经常给我和我兄弟讲故事。
And most of the time.
[AI] 大多数时候。
he told me this story I'm going to share with you now.
[AI] 他告诉了我这个故事，我现在要和你们分享。
The story of what happened
[AI] 发生的事情的故事
when he was a conscripted soldier in the Dutch armed forces
[AI] 当他是荷兰武装部队的应征士兵时
at the beginning of the Second World War.
[AI] 在第二次世界大战开始时。
The Nazis invaded the Netherlands.
[AI] 纳粹入侵荷兰。
Their grim plans were evident.
[AI] 他们冷酷的计划显而易见。
They meant to rule by means of repression.
[AI] 他们打算用镇压的手段来统治。
Diplomacy had failed to stop the Germans.
[AI] 外交手段未能阻止德国人。
Only brute force remained.
[AI] 只剩下蛮力了。
It was our last resort.
[AI] 这是我们最后的办法。
My father was there to provide it.
[AI] 我父亲是来提供的。
As the son of a farmer who knew how to hunt.
[AI] 作为一个懂得打猎的农民的儿子。
my father was an excellent marksman.
[AI] 我父亲是一名出色的射手。
When he aimed. he never missed.
[AI] 当他瞄准的时候。他从未错过。
At this decisive moment in Dutch history
[AI] 在荷兰历史上的这一决定性时刻
my father was positioned on the bank of the river Waal
[AI] 我父亲被安置在瓦尔河畔
near the city of Nijmegen.
[AI] 在奈梅根市附近。
He had a clear shot at the German soldiers who came to occupy a free country.
[AI] 他向前来占领一个自由国家的德国士兵开了一枪。
his country.
[AI] 他的国家。
our country.
[AI] 我们的国家。
He fired. Nothing happened.
[AI] 他开枪了。什么也没发生。
He fired again.
[AI] 他又开枪了。
No German soldier fell to the ground.
[AI] 没有德国士兵倒在地上。
My father had been given an old gun
[AI] 我父亲得到了一把旧枪
that could not even reach the opposite riverbank.
[AI] 甚至无法到达对面的河岸。
Hitler's troops marched on.
[AI] 希特勒的军队继续前进。
and there was nothing my father could do about it.
[AI] 我父亲对此无能为力。
Until the day my father died.
[AI] 直到我父亲去世的那天。
he was frustrated about missing these shots.
[AI] 他对错过这些镜头感到沮丧。
He could have done something.
[AI] 他本可以做点什么的。
But with an old gun.
[AI] 但是用一把旧枪。
not even the best marksman in the armed forces
[AI] 甚至不是军队中最好的射手
could have hit the mark.
[AI] 可能已经击中目标了。
So this story stayed with me.
[AI] 所以这个故事一直伴随着我。
Then in high school.
[AI] 然后在高中。
I was gripped by the stories of the Allied soldiers --
[AI] 我被盟军士兵的故事吸引住了--
soldiers who left the safety of their own homes and risked their lives
[AI] 离开自己安全的家园，冒着生命危险的士兵
to liberate a country and a people that they didn't know.
[AI] 解放一个他们不认识的国家和人民。
They liberated my birth town.
[AI] 他们解放了我的出生地。
It was then that I decided I would take up the gun --
[AI] 就在那时，我决定拿起枪--
out of respect and gratitude for those men and women
[AI] 出于对那些男人和女人的尊重和感激
who came to liberate us.
[AI] 来解放我们的人。
From the awareness that sometimes only the gun
[AI] 从意识到有时只有枪
can stand between good and evil.
[AI] 能站在善与恶之间。
And that is why I took up the gun --
[AI] 这就是我拿起枪的原因--
not to shoot.
[AI] 不要开枪。
not to kill.
[AI] 不要杀人。
not to destroy.
[AI] 不要破坏。
but to stop those who would do evil.
[AI] 而是阻止那些作恶的人。
to protect the vulnerable.
[AI] 保护弱势群体。
to defend democratic values.
[AI] 捍卫民主价值观。
to stand up for the freedom we have to talk here today in Amsterdam
[AI] 为了捍卫自由，我们今天必须在阿姆斯特丹这里讲话
about how we can make the world a better place.
[AI] 关于我们如何让世界变得更美好。
Ladies and gentlemen.
[AI] 女士们，先生们。
I do not stand here today to tell you about the glory of weapons.
[AI] 我今天站在这里不是要告诉你们武器的荣耀。
I do not like guns.
[AI] 我不喜欢枪。
And once you have been under fire yourself.
[AI] 一旦你自己受到攻击。
it brings home even more clearly
[AI] 它更清楚地说明了这一点
that a gun is not some macho instrument to brag about.
[AI] 枪不是吹嘘的大男子主义工具。
I stand here today
[AI] 我今天站在这里
to tell you about the use of the gun as an instrument of peace and stability.
[AI] 告诉你枪支作为和平与稳定的工具的用途。
The gun may be one of the most important instruments of peace and stability
[AI] 枪支可能是和平与稳定的最重要工具之一
that we have in this world.
[AI] 我们在这个世界上所拥有的。
Now this may sound contradictory to you.
[AI] 这听起来可能与你的想法相矛盾。
But not only have I seen with my own eyes
[AI] 但我不仅亲眼看到了
during my deployments in Lebanon. Sarajevo
[AI] 在我在黎巴嫩的部署期间。萨拉热窝
and as the Netherlands' Chief of Defence.
[AI] 作为荷兰的国防部长。
this is also supported by cold. hard statistics.
[AI] 冷空气也支持这一点。硬统计。
Violence has declined dramatically over the last 500 years.
[AI] 在过去500年中，暴力急剧减少。
Despite the pictures we are shown daily in the news.
[AI] 尽管我们每天都在新闻中看到这些图片。
wars between developed countries are no longer commonplace.
[AI] 发达国家之间的战争已不再司空见惯。
The murder rate in Europe
[AI] 欧洲的谋杀率
has dropped by a factor of 30 since the Middle Ages.
[AI] 自中世纪以来下降了30倍。
And occurrences of civil war and repression
[AI] 以及内战和镇压事件
have declined since the end of the Cold War.
[AI] 自冷战结束以来，这一数字一直在下降。
Statistics show that we are living in a relatively peaceful era.
[AI] 统计数字表明，我们生活在一个相对和平的时代。
Why?
[AI] 为什么？
Why has violence decreased?
[AI] 为什么暴力有所减少？
Has the human mind changed?
[AI] 人类的思想改变了吗？
Well. we were talking about the human mind this morning.
[AI] 好今天早上我们在谈论人类的思维。
Did we simply lose our beastly impulses for revenge.
[AI] 我们只是失去了复仇的兽性冲动。
for violent rituals.
[AI] 用于暴力仪式。
for pure rage?
[AI] 为了纯粹的愤怒？
Or is there something else?
[AI] 还是有别的事？
In his latest book. Harvard professor Steven Pinker --
[AI] 在他的新书中。哈佛大学教授史蒂文·平克--
and many other thinkers before him --
[AI] 以及他之前的许多其他思想家--
concludes that one of the main drivers
[AI] 得出结论，主要驱动因素之一
behind less violent societies
[AI] 在不那么暴力的社会背后
is the spread of the constitutional state
[AI] 是宪政国家的传播吗
and the introduction. on a large scale.
[AI] 以及导言。大规模地。
of the state monopoly on the legitimized use of violence --
[AI] 国家对合法使用暴力的垄断--
legitimized by a democratically elected government.
[AI] 被民选政府合法化。
legitimized by checks and balances and an independent judicial system.
[AI] 通过制衡和独立的司法制度使其合法化。
In other words. a state monopoly
[AI] 换句话说。国家垄断
that has the use of violence well under control.
[AI] 这使得暴力的使用得到了很好的控制。
Such a state monopoly on violence. first of all. serves as a reassurance.
[AI] 这样的国家垄断了暴力。首先这是一种安慰。
It removes the incentive for an arms race
[AI] 它消除了军备竞赛的动机
between potentially hostile groups in our societies.
[AI] 在我们社会中潜在的敌对团体之间。
Secondly. the presence of penalties
[AI] 其次惩罚的存在
that outweigh the benefits of using violence
[AI] 这超过了使用暴力的好处
tips the balance even further.
[AI] 这进一步打破了平衡。
Abstaining from violence
[AI] 戒除暴力
becomes more profitable than starting a war.
[AI] 比发动战争更有利可图。
Now nonviolence starts to work like a flywheel.
[AI] 现在，非暴力开始像飞轮一样运转。
It enhances peace even further.
[AI] 它进一步促进了和平。
Where there is no conflict. trade flourishes.
[AI] 没有冲突的地方。贸易繁荣。
And trade is another important incentive against violence.
[AI] 而贸易是反对暴力的另一个重要诱因。
With trade. there's mutual interdependency and mutual gain between parties.
[AI] 与贸易有关。各方之间存在着相互依赖和互利。
And when there is mutual gain. both sides stand to lose more
[AI] 当双方都有利益的时候。双方都会损失更多
than they would gain if they started a war.
[AI] 如果他们发动战争，他们会得到更多。
War is simply no longer the best option.
[AI] 战争不再是最好的选择。
and that is why violence has decreased.
[AI] 这就是暴力减少的原因。
This. ladies and gentlemen.
[AI] 这女士们，先生们。
is the rationale behind the existence of my armed forces.
[AI] 是我的军队存在的理由。
The armed forces implement the state monopoly on violence.
[AI] 武装部队对暴力实行国家垄断。
We do this in a legitimized way
[AI] 我们这样做是合法的
only after our democracy has asked us to do so.
[AI] 只有在我们的民主要求我们这样做之后。
It is this legitimate. controlled use of the gun
[AI] 这是合法的。枪支的控制使用
that has contributed greatly
[AI] 这作出了巨大贡献
to reducing the statistics of war. conflict and violence around the globe.
[AI] 减少战争的统计数字。全球的冲突和暴力。
It is this participation in peacekeeping missions
[AI] 正是这种对维和特派团的参与
that has led to the resolution of many civil wars.
[AI] 这导致了许多内战的解决。
My soldiers use the gun as an instrument of peace.
[AI] 我的士兵们把枪当作和平的工具。
And this is exactly why failed states are so dangerous.
[AI] 这正是失败国家如此危险的原因。
Failed states have no legitimized. democratically controlled use of force.
[AI] 失败的国家没有合法性。民主控制的武力使用。
Failed states do not know of the gun as an instrument of peace and stability.
[AI] 失败的国家不知道枪支是和平与稳定的工具。
That is why failed states can drag down a whole region into chaos and conflict.
[AI] 这就是为什么失败的国家可以把整个地区拖入混乱和冲突。
That is why spreading the concept of the constitutional state
[AI] 这就是为什么要传播宪政国家的概念
is such an important aspect of our foreign missions.
[AI] 这是我们外交任务的一个重要方面。
That is why we are trying to build a judicial system
[AI] 这就是为什么我们正在努力建立一个司法系统
right now in Afghanistan.
[AI] 现在在阿富汗。
That is why we train police officers. we train judges.
[AI] 这就是我们培训警官的原因。我们培训法官。
we train public prosecutors around the world.
[AI] 我们在世界各地培训检察官。
And that is why --
[AI] 这就是为什么--
and in the Netherlands. we are very unique in that --
[AI] 在荷兰。我们在这方面非常独特--
that is why the Dutch constitution states
[AI] 这就是荷兰宪法规定的原因
that one of the main tasks of the armed forces
[AI] 这是军队的主要任务之一
is to uphold and promote the international rule of law.
[AI] 就是要维护和促进国际法治。
Ladies and gentlemen.
[AI] 女士们，先生们。
looking at this gun. we are confronted with the ugly side of the human mind.
[AI] 看看这把枪。我们面临着人类思想丑陋的一面。
Every day I hope that politicians. diplomats. development workers
[AI] 我每天都希望政治家们。外交官。发展工作者
can turn conflict into peace
[AI] 可以把冲突变成和平
and threat
[AI] 和威胁
into hope.
[AI] 进入希望。
And I hope that one day armies can be disbanded
[AI] 我希望有一天军队可以解散
and humans will find a way of living together
[AI] 人类将找到一种共同生活的方式
without violence and oppression.
[AI] 没有暴力和压迫。
But until that day comes.
[AI] 但在那一天到来之前。
we will have to make ideals and human failure
[AI] 我们必须使理想和人类失败
meet somewhere in the middle.
[AI] 在中间相遇。
Until that day comes. I stand for my father
[AI] 直到那一天到来。我代表我父亲
who tried to shoot the Nazis with an old gun.
[AI] 他试图用一把旧枪射杀纳粹。
I stand for my men and women who are prepared to risk their lives
[AI] 我支持那些准备冒生命危险的人
for a less violent world for all of us.
[AI] 为我们所有人创造一个不那么暴力的世界。
I stand for this soldier who suffered partial hearing loss
[AI] 我代表这个部分失聪的士兵
and sustained permanent injuries to her leg.
[AI] 她的腿受了永久伤。
when she was hit by a rocket on a mission in Afghanistan.
[AI] 当她在阿富汗执行任务时被火箭击中。
Ladies and gentlemen.
[AI] 女士们，先生们。
until the day comes when we can do away with the gun.
[AI] 直到有一天我们可以扔掉枪。
I hope we all agree
[AI] 我希望大家都同意
that peace and stability do not come free of charge.
[AI] 和平与稳定不是免费的。
It takes hard work. often behind the scenes.
[AI] 这需要艰苦的工作。通常在幕后。
It takes good equipment and well-trained. dedicated soldiers.
[AI] 它需要良好的设备和训练有素的员工。忠诚的士兵。
I hope you will support the efforts of our armed forces
[AI] 我希望你们支持我们军队的努力
to train soldiers like this young captain
[AI] 训练像这位年轻的上尉这样的士兵
and provide her with a good gun.
[AI] 给她一把好枪。
instead of the bad gun my father was given.
[AI] 给我父亲的不是那把坏枪。
I hope you will support our soldiers when they are out there.
[AI] 我希望当我们的士兵在那里的时候，你们会支持他们。
when they come home
[AI] 当他们回家的时候
and when they are injured and need our care.
[AI] 当他们受伤需要我们照顾的时候。
They put their lives on the line. for us. for you.
[AI] 他们冒着生命危险。对我们来说。为你。
and we cannot let them down.
[AI] 我们不能让他们失望。
I hope you will respect my soldiers.
[AI] 我希望你们尊重我的士兵。
this soldier with this gun.
[AI] 这个拿着枪的士兵。
Because she wants a better world.
[AI] 因为她想要一个更美好的世界。
Because she makes an active contribution to a better world.
[AI] 因为她对一个更美好的世界做出了积极的贡献。
just like all of us here today.
[AI] 就像今天在座的所有人一样。
Thank you very much.
[AI] 非常感谢你。
(Applause)
[AI] （掌声）